Rizzo's I think about faith that's
encouraged to be developed in this
training there's a one should train in developing
there's a one should train in developing
but it comes in that context of five
pounds faith moral Shane my energy and
faith in like it's really all this faith
we have faith in the Buddha I don't you
know the reasoning was a good teaching
it makes sense yeah and I knew you
decide to walk the path
the other one has faith in some form
another yeah in regard to something
faith in the world yeah so you you think
that you believe in family you believe
in sensuality right you think it's gonna
do you could place your faith in but
somehow don't really recognize that
person doesn't develop awareness which
is that's your belief but boy they're
not so now if you recognize that yeah
that is the well then you start feeling
responsibility for your faith as then
you can't be just justifying well this
is my belief oh you realize you choose
to hold that belief so you're
responsible which means you can also
choose to stop holding it so then you
start to scrutinize your own beliefs and
then you might arrive at a better
believe that the truth as a motorist
more wholesome so there's the power of
faith well the power of faith would be
say somebody as fully scrutinize it it's
fully accept responsibility for and then
he realizes what matters freedom from
suffering matters that's that's pretty
much you know whatever people do in the
life is because of how they feel Cyril
why don't I have faith then in something
that actually pertains to this block
absolute fundamental most crucial points
of human existence of a kind of faith it
is to that which is sort of perishable
so in that sense that faith becomes his
power because because of that faith he
then starts to apply himself
into that instruction or teachings on
the simulator unless you start
scrutinizing you're gonna put your faith
in the first walk that comes from comes
your way and you just want one thing for
the requisites a doctor I don't need to
know these things you'll have me but he
might want to help you but he might not
be able as in he himself is unaware that
he's not actually adequate doctor so
unless you stop scrutinizing in as well
you're in a lot of risk but you start
scrutinizing and then you place that
faith correcting somebody is our know
this guy can cure me from this to this
to this you can manage this symptom of
that symptom of some other symptom but
this doctor approves the actual illness
or so it seems I need to find out so in
that sense you develop faith and that
faith is a power if it's placed rather
good because without a faith you
wouldn't start in practice and instead
say like said that like an aria is how
can nobody cycle if he lacks faith as in
could use a bit more faith in surgery
certain aspects that's why he's not free
from sensuality yet by developing faith
has interest ramadi himself that he just
needs to stick to the principle and even
the sensuality will fade the destruction
of senses will go away but by not having
that faith but not remind himself of
just thinking through principles those
things still linger this is it was lack
of faith some some stay monks they have
faith but they live their life with
tears in the eyes painful right there's
no result
they have faith in wholesome qualities
yeah sure because he's still actually
making effort it comes the faith is
inevitable so what are you gonna place
your faith in you in something the world
yeah no that's that's what I mean with
this particular phase of that you start
looking at the mental aspect exactly it
comes down to you either won the world
have faith in it that's something that
friendly disposed towards you oh you
don't have that faith you have faith in
actually renouncing the world you can't
have it both ways so you can't say well
other than us in the world but I also
think this position same place it's how
you accept it or you want to overcome it
that's what I said it's better to even
if you're not necessarily arriving and
any results to still maintain the faith
and enunciation faith in overcoming the
world okay in saying no to
this is delicious
there is a chance that wisdom can arise
out of it but certain wisdom water ice
if you said yes to the world and went
back to the senses because it's
difficult you through reasoning you have
faith but then if there's no results
well my gmail industro because they
never really clarify the reasons for the
practice to begin with just one
inspiration lasted and that's another
thing actually yeah
people confuse faith and inspiration as
well do you think what they feel
inspired and faith faith is that
recognition of this will be beneficial
for me I don't know for sure but it
seems so so because of that recognition
you apply yourself and that's exactly
what will points out when he says even
if even if it hurts even if there are no
results you keep doing it because it
comes out of a recognition of wholesome
what they say but inspiration
inspiration it's like when we were
riding the wave or everything is easy
because you're so inspired it's like a
spiritual honey yes that will have to
run out and you would have been better
off not even giving rise to it but some
people can't help it but once it's
running around its course that's where
the practice starts now if I quit when
you feel like doing it it's when you
don't want to do it and you want to go
back to the world
so basically faith the inspiration would
be intoxication full of intoxication of
your faith like there is a prospect of
escape freedom from suffering see answer
inspired in itself that's other problems
but if that becomes your main main kind
of work where your efforts are rooted in
then you will be in danger
that intoxication will fail that that
energy that you got from the initial
inspiration will have to subside but
events was the sole ground for your
efforts then your efforts will go with
it so that's where the reflexive
reasoning before and next we know I
might be inspired an optic inspired
ready for no more that's also good the
ponies to keep doing the point is to
keep doing it you think of the thing
with this face power it arises seems to
suggest with the other they are the four
powers it seemed to indicate what theirs
are the four things indicate what the
faith is of that it has a really good
wisdom it's really consisting of any
good things yeah yeah because if your
faith is just based on I don't know the
appearance of somebody is talking about
the teaching or something or the
charisma or the energy versus what you
don't want to do the work of
scrutinizing but you just want to ride
off the winds
we must be an adult that's gonna live
with him as if that does anything to you
the only way you will benefit from
another fund is if you start
understanding what opinion on it is but
you know how can you must be another but
if your faith is not rooted in that
blind intoxication then you'll be
scrutinizing how does the person live
what do they teach do they live what
they teach as the CG makes sense does
the teaching pertain to the ultimate
goal the results in liberation if you
start seeing yes or if you're not sure
okay come close I have a closer look ask
more questions to yourself but then if
it seems more right than other things
you can encounter then you have to start
doing it you can't just keep you
distance and expect to understand it and
that's where the faith comes in once you
scrutinized okay I'll start with this
then we'll see you still don't commit to
it blindly
you keep reflecting on what you're doing
but you stop looking for faults as well
and if you start thinking like that from
the standing here exactly if that was if
your efforts are correct if you're
scrutinizing insufficient and then the
energy arising from wisdom that the
whole work what the verification from
freedom from suffering wisdom from
understanding momentum but it's not a
momentum of inspiration isn't I mean
they talk is confusing inspiration I
mean if I people use the word
inspiration for that manner that's fine
but I call if I'd it five minutes ago
it's usually inspiration means you know
it's kind of taking you not you taking
it your face the inspiration takes takes
you you don't but faith you taking
yeah yes inspiration is one faith when
you make a thank you
because you must have faith in wholesome
quality tears faith in wholesome
qualities he read these are wholesome
why they're hosting it's a safety so
they don't like to think like somebody
who starts they don't know why is
wholesome wholesome but they need to
face it that's why you take on the
virtue in the sealer on trust so you
have faith because of some level it's
kind of making a bit of sense that
restraint is better than non restraint
and because of that faith because of
healing to their principle they did is
turn through the faith then then
actually you get to see for yourself
that's when we sought upon his faith
sorry
his previous faith becomes confirmed
confidence in the Dhamma in the
wholesome his holster in that criteria
he sees it for himself now so then for
him faith becomes inconceivable that
faith is gone because now he's confident
so faith is bars implies a degree of
ignorance and you don't know it
to the extent you have nodes to that
extent you have faith in it but not like
faith as I said oh I think that this was
taught all of my problems are now I'm
faith it if I do this I was sorting all
my problems out and that's a like a not
even so subtle shift but many people
would sort of faith in the meditation
technique for example people can invest
a lot so every stuff but the faith is
placed on the content what you're doing
as in if I keep doing is 10 D the
solution of all the problems as in the
Enlightenment resort will happen to me
because I've been not hearing to this
and that's completely blind faith
because they're completely divorced from
any rational recognition of what is
what why is it wholesome to just be
doing this meditation technique am i
understanding anything no but what are
you going after when you're doing a
random random observances you're going
to offer experiences so your faith the
random experiences one of them will be
the right experience so you have faith
is a random experience will do the work
for you as in will result in
enlightening no adhering to wholesome
avoiding unwholesome reflecting upon
unwholesome keeping the precepts any
sense of shame any sense of shame
exactly doing it and there is nothing
composite making an effort yeah no no no
technique will make the effort for you
no technique will give you the wisdom
no no technique will make you have a
sense of shame exactly
people think well these things are
necessary but then technique will get
you to that point but the faith in the
point that's the blind pain and oh come
on it's a mistaken faith the faith
should be in your effort not to the
point the randomly arises sometimes does
something doesn't some novelty
experience it's completely secondary the
faith is in that event has faith in
abandoning unwholesome has faith in
calculating also how do you cultivate
something or abandon something he can no
discerning what I think is how can be
certain if you never make the effort to
think about it before during our efforts
are aimed at suppressing your thinking
and focusing on one point and what not
to get their energy releases its own and
then I'll see you I had faith and I this
energy reason must be so far
if you have energy releases or whatever
it's not teaching about your knee hurts
your back itches there is an energy
release out of a normal to distrain all
those things occur bodily in the body
for you and have nothing to do with
understanding the nature of it so you
should have faith in I have faith in the
possibility of understanding the nature
of things know that I'm what I have
faith in this particular method of
walking or shalini or something whereby
I wanted to think about anything else
if I just adhere to it having faith in
the Buddha myself awake because he makes
you make his own effort yeah he didn't
follow someone so is technique which
understanding of the suffering and fear
from he didn't say oh well by walking
three steps to the left four steps to
the right by watching your nostrils and
observing the movements of your belly or
sensations in your shoulders and whatnot
no he said by understanding suffering
cause of suffering cessation of
suffering in the way that leads to the
cessation full understanding full
understanding missus after thank you the
student you know knowingly for him
knowingly those things are always
knowing knowing knowing he does not
assist as in he knew he understand it
through it through it wasn't like all
this is rose what is it oh it must be
this experience of freedom from
suffering means is understanding it you
just the guesswork just mystifying now
and hoping that is that but the fact
that you don't know that it is means it
isn't because freedom from suffering
comes to knowledge rate he knows that he
knows in the good of his crimes of the
father he knows that he knows now just
he had experience and he is kind of
deduced that he must be understanding
freedom from suffering because
I suffer less suffering glass doesn't
mean you free from danger suffering
suffer less means that you suffer less
due to circumstances between you gonna
suffer more but if you think that
suffering less matters as a measure as
in you suffer less amount but it's still
the suffering all the tape Tabor runs
Dave around and also if you make the
effort
I was gonna say if that's the view means
and if you think that I don't see any
other distinction of full understanding
but I suffer less and fail to see this
because of circumstances because of the
restraint and so on not because of
wisdom so when segment has change and
they will but the suffering hits you
back too late to do anything about it so
yeah if you suffer less on account of
your restraint that's great but telling
itself it's not a solution suffering
still touches you you want to be not
touched by the suffering in the first
place and then you can say you truly not
you're not free from suffering just
circumstantial by if if if either from
suffering is measured of of your
understanding then is that remaining
proteges that will sort of think well
you you could argue then then then then
fine I spent two years because they don't
I spent two years because they don't
really suffer much but it isn't how much
you're exposed to suffering on a
particular basis it doesn't matter what
method is going to say whether you're
prey to suffering as in whether you're
liable to suffering to affect you is it
a possibility exactly I might not suffer
now but is this true for the future if
something happens to me something
unforeseen annexin will i be unaffected
by it and if you're not sure means you
do not know the way are
if you're not sure that you won't be
affected if you're sure that it cannot
affect you because you understood the
way out of suffering then you and you
will know that because if you think
about think about an accident happening
to you in the future and see even that
thought is actually contains the
displeasure of that prospect that
possibility and if you're not free from
suffering that thought will already be
affecting you but if you are evolving
then you know whatever comes to that
thought won't affect your either to have
been extremely convenient you can
disable that well not but you won't
suffer yeah yeah if I lose all my my
things fire fire yeah
will that be affected they've always
disappears and you don't have to go and
start throwing your things away just
well on that thought the hospital is
being taken away is their emotional
resistance to it like it is or something
the prospect that's your work again not
throwing away things or accumulating for
that matter but actually I'm doing that
emotional connection to it cuz that
thing is not undone because you don't
think about it that is its fuel now
thinking about an emotional assumption
connection craving that's why you're
feeling it if you think about it you
stop feeling it that's what so
persistent energy all the way all the
time so do you not see you don't have to cuz
so do you not see you don't have to cuz
then the energy becomes your motivating
and energy effort mindfulness becomes
effortless all of that gets fully fully
converts into confidence faith is
verified what you had faith in that's it
so very find it you don't have faith
that this works because now you know
that it won't is trust so faith the
right faith it's like following wisdom
borrowing the knowledge that you arrive
at borrowing it beforehand as something
to guard you in their direction and then
you arrive at it and that's how you pay
it back but exactly what you said if
that faith is not rooted in their wisdom
you won't be borrowing wisdom for you
when you develop faith you're borrowing
more ignorance there's no reason to
relax
what is solid here only the only time
the only time you would you need to
relax in your practice is when you
assume the pleasures of your senses is
relaxation that's when people want to
relax or the strength from the practice
because they still assume that absence
of effort means relaxation but it
doesn't
wholesome things mean the devastation
but if you don't know that then the
pleasures are kind of unwholesome is
what the realization is distraction
through sight sound smell taste touches
pleasures of sight sound smell taste
after but if you recognize no that's not
that also requires effort so the truly
relaxing thing is thing that it's
effortless thing that is free thing that
doesn't require maintenance things it
doesn't require management things that
don't require fueling and that's not
Donna
so then renunciation is a true
relaxation say no to sensuality is true
way of relaxing but not to the one who
still has the view that pertains to
sensuality really doesn't see the danger
in it then single to society with me
like saying on to the pleasure of it and
pleasure for me means relaxation so then
I am saying no to realization but if you
have faith in the renunciation and
remove your faith in the pleasure of
senses which is what you think
relaxation is you will come to see that
yet you were mistaken the true absolute
this thing is renunciation it's a
negative it's not about doing this to
that it's about not doing waste of that
and that's after your freedom from
unwholesome states
that's effortless yeah sure could we try
it requires knowledge these initial
initially servant to get a sense of the
direction of the practice cuz if you
just stick with I faith in this of that
are you gonna scrutinize it further
you don't effective money further well
then it's up all taken away and was not
just faith you would you wouldn't be
able to integer cosmic John give me this
sure you yeah exactly
yeah exactly
look that's women the right faith it's
like pouring of that which you want to
achieve of course you can be very
generic inaccurate just following
something without much without
concentrated something's in it substance
that you need but if you scrutinize it
clarifies further then your faith
becomes more accurate as well and then
your faith actually pertains in a more
concentrated manner for that which
you're trying to achieve
why because you're scrutinized it's been
the southern oh sorry the one who kind
of puts the faith first as the weakest
of the faculties cuz he just he just
takes the faith and does what he did
sent through that faith which in scope
it's much more limited than for somebody
who actually discerns even the faith so
he puts the discernment factor first the
dominant side of course Thomas OD will
carries on faith trees disturbance I'm
gonna study will be developing his
discernment through his own faith he put
faith first as believe it first it's
much slower and more riskier today you
could get that back in the day with a
lot so our arms around et Ching and so
on but today it's moving more like the
other way well so stuff you here has
nothing to do with the Dhamma so you
need to first make the effort to undo
all the wrong notions of what you think
that means and then start practicing
right so you can't afford to just run
off faith because sooner or later
something's completely wrong and you
won't see it that stage
but putting the salmon first it's much
more unpleasant more exacting will drive
more doubt you suffered millions of
lifetime's you will suffer millions or
lifetime what is more lifetime more
because at least you're trying to
practice them alright so yeah even if
you suffer as the bill said it means you
spend the rest of your life in tears or
restraint and then get anywhere it's
still worth something so bad because you
never do that for years and years and
years you never do if you don't if you
can't figure it all out it was confusing
faith in cultivating wholesome qualities
please come back to the fundamentals
understand easy to understand yeah
well that's right speaking searcher okay
well in the fundamental matter it
wouldn't be particular or faith in this
of that very thing recognition of
wholesome if I stick to this can only
result in good which is buying its
wholesome I don't see directly but I
have a good faith there it is
so I'd say my body and the speech and
the mine just you're staying from
killing you're lying and something
you'll substained from unwholesome
speech so gossip careless chatter and
all these things that are unwholesome
that part of you should abstain from
that she abstained from malicious speech
false speech devices beat till you go
further you abstain from thoughts no
field will and cruelty so you know
you're not gonna say anything do
anything but you stop entertaining
thoughts as well for such nature that's
the message that's the meditation
technique